one kind of funny statement is a toogy a
toogy and we we usually use T for that
opposed to P or Q or R we use the symbol
t for a topology this is the statement
that is always true and can never be
false so for instance consider the
statement that dog is a mammal well that
statement is always true doesn't matter
which dog you're referring to in the
concept of what a dog is implicitly is
the concept that it is going to be a
mammal that is one of the properties of
being a dog so if I if I have the
statement that dog is a mammal it does
not matter which dog I'm referring to so
this statement is always true
irregardless of my inputs so this is
sort of play some funny games when it
comes to looking at what the truth
tables are so I'm going to imagine that
I've got the statement I want to look at
what T or p is where I've got a toy T
and A ology it's truth table is very
simple it's just always true right the
the topology can never be false so it's
just true true true true everywhere and
then I also have this other statement p
p is just a normal old statement here so
it can be true or false so maybe its
first possibility will be true and a
second possibility will be
false and then if I want to take a
topology or some statement remember or
is true if if one of the two are going
to be true but the ology is always true
so it's always the case that one of them
is going to be true here so there's two
truths there which is good enough to
give me a true here there's only one
true here but that's fine it's an or
statement I only need one of them to be
true so that's going to be true there as
well I can also have contradictions
contradictions are labeled by a c now
for contradiction and this is a
statement that is always false so this
is an example that dog is a reptile
again in the notion of a dog it is
implicit that dogs are mammals and not
reptiles so it can never be true that
that dog is a reptile so this means that
in our truth table whenever I have a c
it is going to be a column of all
falsehoods so here I'm going to have a
false and here I'm going to have a false
and then I've also done a simple example
I'm trying to look at C and P where p is
just some other statements so let's fill
in a couple different possibilities for
p could be true and it could be false
and then if I want to look at my final
conclusion which was C and P remember
and requires both of them to be true but
because we have my contradiction always
been false it will never be the case
that both of them are true and so since
there's one false there there's going to
be a false there since there's a false
there there's going to be false there as
well so when I had an or statement with
a a a topology it forced that to be toy
it made it always going to be true if
you if you took or a toy you could just
take the value of the toy would be
always true if you take and a
contradiction then it's just going to
make it into its own contradiction which
is going to be all falses in other words
I can say that that c and P is a
contradiction it will always be false as
this table I mentioned and as we saw in
the previous slide if I take t or P that
is always true and so it is always a
topology